A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice, Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Joseph Schull FA1712
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice, Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Joseph Schull
1979-1997
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Schull, Joseph (1961)
FA1712
2.62 Cubic Feet 6 boxes (4 letter document containers and 2 legal document containers)
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Subject Files
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Schull started at the Ford Foundation in 1991 as an assistant program officer in the International Affairs program. By 1993, he was promoted to deputy director of the International Affairs program. In 1996, Ford Foundation program areas were restructured, and he became deputy director of the Governance and Civil Society program within the Peace and Social Justice division. The Governance and Civil Society program's overarching goals were to improve governmental performance and accountability, find new approaches to implement public policies, and enhance the role of civic organizations in promoting democratic values. Schull worked to fund new initiatives in Russia and Eastern Europe. Schull left the Ford Foundation for Warburg Pincus in 1998.
Scope and Contents
Joseph Schull served as a program officer and deputy director of the International Affairs and the Governance and Civil Society programs at the Ford Foundation between 1991 and 1998. His work focused on creating new foundation initiatives in Russia and Eastern Europe. The collection is comprised of trip reports, articles on civil society issues, Ford program review materials, background papers, policy documents, and conference materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:115.
Ford Foundation; Program development -- Europe, Eastern
- Subject Files, 1979-1997; 1; 2.62 Cubic Feet 6 containers
  - Czech/Slovakia Background Materials, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    International Network for Democratic Solidarity
    Czechoslovakia in the Middle of Transition, Musil
    Needs Assessment of the Czech and Slovak Federal Repblic for the US Rule of Law Task Force, Roslyn A. Mazer
    Czech Health System Papers
  - Ford Foundation Conference on Czechoslovakia, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - East European Regional Background Information, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Soros Foundation
    Civil Resistance in The East European and Soviet Revolutions, Adam Roberts
    International Cultural Centre
    The Constitutional Commission of the Diet
  - Human Rights, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    World Conference on Human Rights
    State Crimes of Previous Regimes: Knowledge, Accountability, and the Policing of the Past
    The University of Birmingham Human Rights Law and Practice Programme
    Amnesty International and Non-governmental entities
    Treatment and Protection of Minorities
    Human Rights - The International Bill of Human Rights
  - Hungary Background, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    Re-establishment of the Rule of Law in Hungary
    Philosophy Department Budapest
    Hungary's Road to Systemic Change: The Opposition Roundtable
    United Nations Research Institute for Social Development
  - Inter-Group Relations, 1979-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    Ford Foundation Ethnic Conflict Meeting
    Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars
    Common Security Network
    United Nations - Study on the Rights of Persons Belonging to Ethnic, Religious and Linguistic Minorities
  - Legal Training Russia, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9, Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Media Projects - Eastern Europe - Media Education, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Poland: Romaszewski, 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Russian Press Coverage of NGOs, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Society for Reform of Criminal Law - Vincent Del Buono, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Trip Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Moscow - February 1990; March 1990
    Hungary, Poland, and East Germany, February 1990
    Budapest, January 1990
    Budapest and Vienna, January 1990
    Poland, October 1990
    Prague, Vienna, Moscow, August 1989
  - Local Governance in the Former Soviet Union and Central and Eastern Europe, Miriam Aukerman, 1995 June (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Evaluation of Ford Foundation Programs in Russia and Eastern Europe, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - FY95 Biennial Program Review, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - International Affairs Program (IAP) Staff Meetings, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Civil Society Articles, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Civil Society at Issue in the Czech Republic, Jiri Pehe
    Bowling Alone: America's Declining Social Capital, Robert D. Putnam
    The Search for Civil Society and Democracy in China, Tony Saich
    "American Exceptionalism" Revisited: The Role of Civil Society, Daniel Bell
    Review Essay, On Civil Society: Why Eastern Europe's Revolutions Could Succeed, Michael Ignatieff
    American Survey - The Solitary Bowler
    The Virtue of Civil Society, Edward Shils
  - Conference on "Assessing Programmatic Effects to Foster Democratization in the Newly Independent States" - Articles, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 21-22, Box 5, Folder 23)
    In the Name of Democracy: US Policy Toward Latin America in the Reagan Years, Thomas Carothers
    The Comparative Survey of Freedom: Experiences and Suggestions, Raymond Duncan Gastil
    Political Democracy: Conceptual and Measurement Traps, Kenneth A. Bollen
    Assessing and Enhancing the Impact of Democratic Development Projects: A Practitioner's Perspective, Stephen Golub
    Passages to Peace: The Diary of a Decade, Robert Karl Manoff
    Participant Biographies
    Problems of Defining Democracy: A Workshop Paper, Ivan Sigal
    Building Democracy: USAID's Strategy
    The Committee on American-Russian Relations Special Opinion of Russian Federation Constitutional Court Judges, E.M. Ametislov
    Political Positions and Composition of Factions at the VII Congress of People's Deputies
    The Referendum and After, Edward Kline
    State-Building in Post-Soviet Russia: The Chicago Boys and the Decline of Administrative Capacity, Peter J. Stavrakis
    The Popular Bases of Anti-Reform Politics in Russia, Stephen Whitefield and Geoffrey Evans
    Regionalism, the Soft State and the Transformation Process, Peter J. Stavrakis
    The New Russia: Troubled Transformation, Gail W. Lapidus
    Army and National Security of Kazakhstan, Assan Nougmanov
    The European Humanitarian University
    Ukraine Political Parties and Organisations, April 1992
  - Moscow Visit Correspondence and Soviet-American Foundation "Cultural Initiative", 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Union of Advocates (Russia), 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Interlegal Research Center (Russia), 1995 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Rekosh, Ed, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Philanthropy and Nonprofits - Articles and Correspondence, 1989-1996 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Review of the Draft Law for the Russian Federation "On Noncommercial Organizations" - Comments by the International Center for Not-For-Profit Law (ICNL)
    Exporting Civil Society: Confessions of a "Foreign Legal Expert," E. Blake Bromley
    Use of Fiscal Agents: A Trap for the Unwary, John A. Edie
    Bill of the Slovak National Council on foundations
    The Scope and Rationale for the Nonprofit Sector: Lessons from Western Experience, Lester M. Salamon
    United Way International: Initiative in Russia and the Newly Independent States of the former Soviet Union
    Law and Associations and Foundations: Comments on Bulgarian Draft Law of May 15, 1992
    Proposal Summary and Progress Report: Action Research Study of Developmental and Management Assistance Needs of Nonprofit Organizations
    Basic information about the non-profit sector in the Czech Republic
  - Bosnia, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Chechnya War, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Ford Foundation Area Studies Initiative, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Community Development Finance Initiative (CDFI), 1996 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Central European Electoral Systems Symposium Report, Budapest, Hungary, International Foundation for Electoral Systems, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - The Political Climate of Russia's Regions: Voters and Deputies, 1991-1993, A. Sobianin, E. Gel'man and O. Kaiunov (Moscow, Russia), 1994 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Central European Electoral System Symposium, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Free and Fair: Towards Democratic Governance
    El Salvador: Recent Elections in Historical Perspective, Jose Z. Garcia
    Elections and Democracy in Central America, John A. Booth and Mitchell A. Seligson
    United Nations General Assembly Agenda Items, November 1991
    The Geography of the April 25 (1993) Russian Referendum, Ralph S. Clem and Peter R. Craumer
    Articles in Russian
  - Network of Institutes and Schools of Public Administration in Central and Eastern Europe (NISPAcee) Bylaws - Association of Legal Entities, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Network of Institutes and Schools of Public Administration in Central and Eastern Europe (NISPAcee) - Public Administration in Transition, Jak Jabes and Mirko Vintar, Third Annual Conference Held in Bled, Slovenia, 1995 March 23-25 (Box 6, Folder 37)